片名：时间简史
改编自史蒂芬·霍金《时间简史》一书
是先有鸡还是先有蛋？
Which came first the chicken or the egg?
宇宙有起源吗?
Did the universe have a beginning...
如果有 那么在宇宙之前又是什么？
and if so,what happened before then?
宇宙从何而来
Where did the universe come from...
它又将去向何方？
and where is it going?
运气好 嗯
Luck. Luck. Well...
我们都很幸运
we have been very lucky
我是说 我的家人 史蒂芬和所有人
I mean,my family and Stephen and everybody.
曾经多灾多难 关键是我们生存下来了
You have your disasters,but the point is that we have survived.
每个人都面临着灾难 一些人消失了
Everybody has disasters,and yet some people disappear...
再也见不到了
and are never seen again.
飞弹总是让人绷紧神经
Flying bombs are very alarming.
它们呼啸而来
They came buzzing over...
然后戛然而止
and then they would cut out.
你听到嘭的一声 你知道你没有被炸
And when you heard the bang,you knew it wasn't you...
你继续吃饭或者做其他的事
so you went back to your meal or whatever.
但是真的有个炸弹掉在我们的房子边上
But one did fall quite close to our house...
震破了玻璃
and it blew the back windows out...
碎玻璃片像尖刀一样打到对面的墙上
so that the glass was sticking dagger points all out of the opposite wall.
当史蒂芬要出生时 我们决定
When Stephen was born,we decided. ..
他最好是出生在牛津
He'd better be born in Oxford.
所以当我呆在医院的时候
So while I was staying in the hospital...
我去了牛津的布莱克威尔医院
I went to Blackwell's in Oxford...
我买了一本天文图集
and I bought an astronomical atlas.
我的一个弟媳说
One of my sisters-in-law said...
"这是你做的很有预见性的一件事"
"This is a very prophetic thing for you to have done."
时间有多真实？
How real is time?
时间有没有终点？
Will it ever come to an end?
过去和未来有什么区别？
Where does the difference between the past and the future come from?
为什么我们能回忆起过去
Why do We remember the past. ..
而不是将来？
But not the future?
我还记得那天
I can remember the day...
我们经过伦敦 然后灯火管制刚结束
when we traveled through London and the blackout was over.
火车仍然在行驶
And the trains,instead of being shut in...
通过火车的百叶窗看去
by blinds so that you just traveled in a train...
我们正经过一座座的铁路桥
we were coming over one of the bridges...
看到灯光闪耀 灯光消逝的地方
and all the lights well,such lights as were left
便是伦敦城区 那也是一个星光闪耀的夜晚
were on in London,but it was also a completely starry night...
你能看到那些星光 非常漂亮
and you could see the light. It was beautiful.
我记得我们都常常躺在草坪上 透过望远镜
I remember we all used to lie on the grass,looking straight up through a telescope...
仰望璀璨的星空
and seeing the wonders of the stars.
史蒂芬总是充满了好奇
Stephen always had a strong sense of wonder...
我知道那些星星吸引了他
and I could see that the stars would draw him...
还有比星星还要深远的东西
and further than the stars.
我出生于伽利略逝世
I was born exactly 300 years...
300周年纪念日
after the death of Galileo.
我估计有二十万婴儿
I estimate that about 200,000 other babies...
在那天出生
were also born that day.
我不知道他们中是否有些人
I don't know whether any of them...
后来对天文学感兴趣
was later interested in astronomy.
我最初的记忆是伊泽贝尔
My first memory is of Isobel...
推着老旧的
pushing a rather antiquated...
马车改装的婴儿车在北方大道上走着
carriage-built pram along North Road...
史蒂芬和玛丽在车内
with Stephen and Mary in it...
看上去非常大
sort of looking very large...
因为他们大大的脑袋 粉红的脸颊 十分引人注目
because they had large heads and pink cheeks,and they were very noticeable.
他们看上去和常人不同
They all looked different from ordinary people.
我记得到霍金家拜访
I can remember visiting the Hawking home...
哦 好多次了
oh,several times.
如果留下来吃晚饭的话
It was the sort of place where,if invited to stay to supper...
你可以 额
you might,uh...
可以和小史蒂芬说说话
be allowed to have your conversation with Stephen...
但是其他家庭成员会坐在
but the rest of the family would be sitting...
桌边阅读
at the table reading a book...
在我的观念里这样做是不允许的
a behavior which was not really approved of in my circle...
但是霍金一家却很宽容
but which was tolerated from the Hawkings...
他们看起来
because they were recognized to be...
非常特别 智商很高
very eccentric,highly intelligent...
非常聪明
very clever people...
但是还是有一点古怪
but still a bit odd.
在我的印象中 霍金家族中
My impression of the Hawking family was that they were all like that...
只有史蒂芬看上去
except for Stephen,who seemed to be...
是一位正常的成员
the only normal member of the family.
史蒂芬常常猜想自己知道 我认为
Stephen used to reckon he knew,I think it was...
有11条进房间的路线 我只找到10条
11 ways of getting into the house,and I could only find ten.
我不是很确定那一条路在哪里
I'm not sure where the other way was.
房子的北面是一间自行车棚
On the north side of the house was a bicycle shed.
有前后门
It had a door at the front and a door at the back.
车棚上面有个窗户通往L型的房间
Above that,there was a Window into the L-shaped room...
前面有个拐角你可以从那里
and at the front you could get sort of around the corner...
上到屋顶去
onto the roof ..
从那里
And from that level...
你能到达主楼屋顶
you could get onto the main roof.
我想其中一条路是
I think one of the ways...
史蒂芬可以从主楼屋顶进去
Stephen could get in was on the main roof.
要我说 他比我会爬得多
As I say,he was a much better climber than I was.
我仍然不知道第11条路是什么
I still didn't know what the 11th one was.
在20世纪以前
Before the 20th century...
人们认为宇宙会永远存在
it was thought that the universe had existed forever...
或形成于过去某个时间点
or had been created at some time in the past...
跟我们今天观测到的差不多
more or less as we observe it today.
人们觉得这样很有说服力
People found comfort in the thought...
尽管他们会衰老和死亡
that even though they may grow old and die...
而宇宙是亘古不变的
the universe was eternal and unchanging.
我不再和霍金玩那个游戏
I gave up playing games with Stephen...
哦 那时候他生病了 大概12岁
oh,when he was ill that time when he was about 12...
因为他开始对游戏异常认真
because he started taking games terribly seriously.
我们玩的是《大富翁》
We had Monopoly...
首先
and first of all...
在《大富翁》棋盘上建起贯穿的铁路
the Monopoly board sprang railways going across it. ..
以增加复杂性
To add to the complications...
后来《大富翁》满足不了他的需求
and then Monopoly just wasn't adaptable enough.
他开始玩更可怕的游戏《王朝》
He ended up with a fearful game called Dynasty...
我不会玩这种游戏 我从没玩过
which,as far as I can make out I never played it
他就会一直玩 因为这游戏没有终点
went on forever because there was no way of ending it.
在我看来 快要取代生活了
It was almost a substitute for living,as far as I could make out.
他在游戏上花费一个又一个小时
It took hours and hours and hours.
我认为这是个非常可怕的游戏
I thought it was a perfectly terrible game.
我难以想象有人能花这么多时间
I couldn't imagine anyone getting taken up with that.
但是史蒂芬有很复杂的思维
But Stephen always had a very complicated mind...
我觉得就是因为
and I felt as much as anything...
这种复杂度吸引了他
it was the complication of it that appealed to him.
我高中的时候 我学到
When I was in high school,I learned that light...
来自遥远星系的光会发生红移
from distant galaxies was shifted to the red.
那意味着它们在远离我们
This meant that they were moving away from us...
宇宙在膨胀
and that the universe was expanding.
但是我不相信
But I didn't believe it.
一个静态的宇宙看起来更加自然
A static universe seemed much more natural.
它可能已经存在
It could have existed...
并且永远存在下去
and could continue to exist forever.
我们当时在讨论
We were discussing the possibility...
生命自然产生的可能性
of the spontaneous generation of life...
我认为从史蒂芬的讨论中
and I think that Stephen made a remark...
不仅能看出他已经想到这一点
which indicated not only that he'd thought of this...
他甚至已经
but he'd even also...
对这一过程所需的时间
come across some calculations..
做了一些计算
as to how long it might take.
那一刻
At that time,
我对其中一位朋友 约翰·麦克莱纳说
I think I made a comment...to one of my friends,John McClenahan...
"我觉得史蒂芬这个人"
"I think that Stephen...
"能力非凡"
will turn out to be unusually capable."
我不确定我当时就是这么说的
I don't think I put it in quite those words...
但我做了类似这样的评价
but I made some such remark to him...
约翰并不认同
and he disagreed.
所以我们打了个赌
And so we made a bet on the subject.
用我们小时候的方法
In our childish way,we bet...
赌注是一袋糖果
a bag of sweets on the issue.
顺便说一句 我认为我敢赌我是正确的
And incidentally,I reckon that my bet has come correct...
我觉得他该付我赌注
and I think I'm entitled to payment...
虽然我现在还没收到
which has not yet been made.
宇宙膨胀
The expansion of the universe...
暗示着一种可能性
suggested the possibility...
宇宙起源于
that the universe had a beginning...
过去的某个时间点
at some time in the past.
宇宙起源的时间点
The point at which the universe may have started out. ..
被称作大爆炸
Became known as the Big Bang.
他第一年在圣阿尔本兹学校的时候
The first year he was at St. Albans School...
成绩倒数第三名
he came,I think,third from the bottom.
我对他说 "好吧 史蒂芬"
I said,"Well,Stephen...
"你真的想变得那么差吗"
do you really have to be as far down as that?"
他说道
And he said,"Well...
"很多人都没有做得更好"
a lot of other people didn't do much better."
他一点也不在意
He was quite unconcerned.
不知为何 他总是被认为
Somehow he was always recognized...
很聪明
as being very bright. ..
事实上他有一年获得过神学奖
And in fact they gave him the Divinity Prize one year.
这没有什么奇怪的 因为他爸爸在他很小的时候就常常给他
That was not surprising because his father used to read him...
朗读一些圣经的故事
Bible stories from a very early age...
他对那些故事很熟悉
and he knew them all very well...
他对宗教的一些事非常精通
and he was quite well-versed in religious things...
然而我不认为他是通过大量的练习才熟悉的
although I don't think he makes a great deal of practice of it now.
每个人都会谈论神学
Everybody used to argue theology.
那是一个好的安全的话题
That's a good,safe subject.
你不需要事实或者
You don't need any facts or...
分散注意力
distracting things like that.
如果你参与讨论
If you go in for arguing
你可以愉快地辩论任何事
you know,debating you can quite happily debate about anything...
包括神学
including theology...
上帝存在及其形式
and the existence or otherwise of God.
一些人会厌倦了
And then someone gets bored ...
就会谈论星际旅行 或者类似这些的
or Journey Into Space comes on,or something like that...
然后讨论到此结束
and the argument breaks up.
在亘古不变的宇宙中
In an unchanging universe...
我们可以想象是上帝于过去的某个时间
one can imagine that God created the universe...
创造了宇宙
at literally any time in the past.
另一方面
On the other hand...
如果宇宙在膨胀
if the universe is expanding...
那可能有物理原因
there may be physical reasons...
为什么一定要有起源呢
why there had to be a beginning.
宇宙的膨胀并不排除创造者
An expanding universe does not preclude a creator...
但是它在上帝是何时创世这方面
but it does place limits...
有局限性
on when he might have carried out his job.
我们一家到了印度
When the family went to India...
史蒂芬也来和我们一起住一年
it was arranged that Stephen should come and live with us for a year.
他认为我们
He decided it would be nice...
晚上应该跳苏格兰舞是很好的
that we should have...Scottish dancing in the evening.
提醒你一下 这是一间很普通的房子
Mind you,this was quite an ordinary house...
但是我们有很多房间和一个大厅
but we had rather a lot of room and a large hall...
我们买了一些唱片
and so we bought some records...
和一本消遣的书
and a book about what to do...
史蒂芬开始主持
and Stephen took charge.
他坚持让你穿夹克打领带
And he insisted you put on a jacket and a tie.
他来当晚会的主持
And then he was the master of the proceedings.
史蒂芬很认真地在做
And Stephen took it very seriously.
但他喜欢跳舞 发现了吗？
But then he liked dancing,you see?
有四位物理学家与我同级
There were four physicists in my year
戈登·贝瑞
Gordon Berry...
里查德·布莱恩
Richard Bryan...
史蒂芬
Stephen...
和我自己
myself.
我对史蒂芬最初的印象是
I first remember Stephen...
有一次 我和戈登吃完饭去史蒂芬的房间
on an occasion when Gordon and I went up after dinner to his room...
找他
to try to find him.
史蒂芬正在那里
And Stephen was up there...
那儿有一箱啤酒
with a crate of beer...
慢慢地喝着啤酒
slowly drinking his way through it.
他只有17岁 不允许去酒吧
He was only 17. He couldn't legally go into a pub.
他很小就去了牛津大学读书
He'd gone up to Oxford ridiculously early.
我们常常聚会
We used to have what we called a gathering net.
组织啤酒派对或者类似的活动
We used to organize a beer party and various things like that...
以邀请尽可能多的新生
to gather all these collar as many freshman as we could get...
让他们加入划船俱乐部
to get them to join the Boat Club.
我们就是这样认识他的
And that's how we collected him,you see?
但是史蒂芬的问题是
But the question always with Stephen was...
"我们应该让他做第一批的八个舵手之一"
"Should we make him the cox of the first eight...
"还是第二批？"
or the second eight?"
有些舵手比较冒险
Well,coxes can be adventurous...
有些则很沉稳
and some coxes can be very steady people.
他属于冒险的那一类
He was rather an adventurous type.
你永远也不知道他接下来会干什么
You never knew quite what he was going to do...
当他和船员一起的时候
when he went out with the crew.
他有时候会想些自己的事情
I think he used to bring his work with him into the boat sometimes.
在船上他思维的齿轮开始转动
His sort of thinking gear was going...
在不同层次上
on different levels.
我们被要求阅读
We were asked to read chapter 10...
一本书的第十章 书名叫电磁学
in a book called Electricity and Magnetism...
由布里尼夫妇所著 一个不太可能的组合
by Bleaney and Bleaney,an unlikely combination
他们是夫妻档
a husband-and-wife team
在第十章的最后部分 有13个问题
and at the end of that chapter,there were 13 questions...
都是具有挑战性的问题
all of them final honors questions.
我很快发现我一个都不会做
I discovered very rapidly that I couldn't do any of them.
理查德和我一起做了一个星期
Richard and I worked together for the week...
我们做出了1道半
and we managed to do 1 1/2 questions...
我们感到很骄傲
which we felt very proud of.
戈登拒绝外援
Gordon refused all assistance...
独立做出了1道题
and managed to do one all by himself.
史蒂芬 像往常一样 甚至还没开始
Stephen,as always,hadn't even started...
但是第二天早上 他9点钟进房间
but the next morning,he went' up to his rooms at 9:00. ..
我们回来是12点 也可能是12点5分
And we came back about 12:00,maybe five past 12:00...
史蒂芬随后也来了 我们在大学门口的长廊碰到
and down came Stephen,and we were in the college gateway,the lodge.
"啊 霍金" 我说 "你做出了多少"
"Ah,Hawking," I said,"how many have you managed to do,then?"
"好吧" 他说 "我只有时间做前十道"
"Well," he said,"I've only had time to do the first ten."
在那一刻 我们认识到我们不仅仅不是一路人
I think at that point we realized that it's not just we weren't in the same street.
我们根本就不是一类人
We weren't on the same planet.
我曾算过
I once calculated...
我在牛津的三年里
that I did about 1,000 hours' work...
做过1 000个小时的工作
in the three years I was at Oxford
平均每天一小时
an average of an hour a day.
我不会因为不勤于工作而感到骄傲
I am not proud of this lack of work.
我只是在描述我当时的态度
I am just describing my attitude at the time...
当时就觉得没有什么是值得努力的
an attitude that nothing was worth making an effort for.
每个星期的课外辅导他都做些研究
He used to produce his work every week for tutorial...
因为他从来不保留笔记
and,as he never kept any notes...
草稿或者类似这些资料
or papers or that sort of thing...
离开我房间的时候 他都把那些会扔到我的垃圾桶里
on leaving my room,he would normally throw it in my wastepaper basket.
当他和其他一些大学生一起做研究
And when he was with other undergraduates at the tutorial...
他们看到这些时 完全吓坏了
and they saw this happen,they were absolutely horrified...
因为他们认为 他只要半小时就完成的工作
'cause they thought,he did this work in probably half an hour...
如果他们能在一年内完成
If they could have done it in a year,
他们都不会扔到废纸篓里
they wouldn't have thrown it in the wastepaper basket.
而是把它们裱起来挂到墙上
They would've put it in a frame on their walls.
由于我疏于学习
Because of my lack of work...
我打算解决理论物理的问题
I had planned to get through the final exam...
来通过我的期末考试
by doing problems in theoretical physics...
并避开需要事实性知识的问题
and avoiding any questions that required factual knowledge.
我做的不是很好
I didn't do very well.
我处在一等和二等学位的边界
I was on the borderline between a first- and second-class degree...
我不得不通过面试来决定我能够获得第几等
and I had to be interviewed to determine which I should get.
他们询问我的未来计划
They asked me about my future plans.
我回答到 如果他们给我第一等
I replied,if they gave me a first...
我就会去剑桥大学
I would go to Cambridge.
如果我获得二等学位
If I only got a second...
我就留在牛津
I would stay in Oxford.
他们给了我一等学位
They gave me a first.
我带着史蒂芬和他的弟弟
I drove Stephen and his young brother...
去沃本公园
out to Woburn Park...
他爬上一棵树
and he climbed a tree.
我想他在测试自己 我没有意识到
He was testing himself out,I think. I didn't realize.
他能够爬树
He did manage to climb a tree...
沿着树枝把自己弄下来
and go along a branch of it and get himself down.
我想他开始认识到自己的双手
I think he began to notice that his hands...
没有曾经那么好用了
were less useful than they had been...
但是他没有告诉我们
but he didn't tell us.
大学里有些垂直的楼梯
Univ has these square staircases...
圆角但却是垂直的
which are round but they're square.
他从一个房间出来
It was just coming down from one of the rooms.
史蒂芬从楼梯上摔了下来
Steve actually fell on the stairs coming downstairs...
一直滚到底部
and kind of bounced all the way down to the bottom.
我不知道他是否失去了意识 但他失忆了
I don't know if he lost consciousness,but he lost his memory.
我们把他弄到一个地方 不是我房间也不是别人的房间
We took him to either my room or someone's room.
他第一个问题就问 "我是谁？"
The first question of course was,"Who am I?"
我们告诉他 "你是史蒂芬·霍金"
We told him,"You're Steve Hawking."
接下来他立马又问了一遍 "我是谁？"
Right away he would ask again,"Who am I?"
"史蒂芬·霍金"
"Steve Hawking."
接着 过了几分钟 他想起他是史蒂芬·霍金
Then,after a couple of minutes,he remembered he was Steve Hawking.
然后我们问他 "你还记得星期天晚上"
Then we'd say,"Do you remember going down to the bar...
"你去酒吧喝酒么？"
and having a drink on Sunday night?"
或者 "你还记得星期一我们在河上划船么？"
Or,"Do you remember coxing on the river on Monday?"
他的记忆逐渐恢复了
And his memory came back gradually...
直到他能记起几天前的一些事 然后是几小时前
until he could remember the previous day's events,and then the previous hour...
后来的两个小时他能记起每一件事
and by the end of the two hours,he could remember everything.
问题是 "你可能因为这个损伤了"
The question was,"Well,maybe you've lost...
"一些脑细胞"
some of your mind because of this."
然后史蒂芬说 "这样的话 我要参加门萨考试"
And so Steve decided,"Well,I'll take the Mensa test."
我们回应道 "你一定会进的"
We said,"Of course you'll get in."
他回来很高兴他能够进入门萨
But he came back delighted he was able to get into Mensa.
极其欣喜
Absolutely delighted.
我感觉理论物理
I felt that there were two areas...
有两个领域
of theoretical physics...
我在剑桥可能会研究的两个领域
I might study at Cambridge.
一个是宇宙学 研究宏观
One was cosmology,the study of the very large.
另一个是基本粒子
The other was elementary particles...
研究微观
the study of the very small.
然而 我认为基础粒子
However,I thought elementary particles...
缺乏吸引力
were less attractive...
因为没有合适的理论
because there was no proper theory.
他们所要做的
All they could do...
就是粒子的分类
was arrange the particles in families...
就像植物学
like in botany.
而在宇宙学里 换句话说
In cosmology,on the other hand...
有定义明确的理论
there was a well-defined theory
爱因斯坦的相对论
Einstein's general theory of relativity.
那一年很冷
It was a very cold year...
维鲁拉米恩池塘
and the ice on Verulamium Pond...
都结了冰
it was frozen there...
我们一起出去滑冰
and we all went skating.
史蒂芬滑的相当好
And Stephen managed to skate fairly well...
但是后来 他离我非常的近
but then,he and I were close together.
他滑冰的水平不是很高
He wasn't skating in a very advanced way...
但我会那样滑
but nor was I,if it comes to that.
他摔倒了
He fell...
爬不起来
and he couldn't get up.
我带着他来到咖啡馆暖身
So I took him to a café to warm up...
他告诉我关于这件事的一切
and he told me then all about it.
并且是确诊的
And it was diagnosed.
我坚持要见他的医生
I insisted on going to see his doctor...
因为不管他还能活多久
because it seemed to me however long you're going to live...
我都想知道有没有什么方法或什么人能够帮助他
there's probably something someone can do about it
至少能让人更容易接受
at least anyhow to make things easier for people.
我不想提医生的名字
I won't mention the doctor's name...
我和他在伦敦的诊所见面
but I got to see him at the London Clinic.
他见到我很惊奇 我竟然不辞劳苦地找到他
He was rather surprised that I should bother to come 'round to see him.
毕竟 我只是史蒂芬的母亲
After all,I was only Stephen's mother.
他非常友好 他同意和我正式会面
He was quite nice. He agreed to see me in a rather grand way.
他说道 "是的 非常抱歉"
And he said,"Yes,it's all very sad.
"才华横溢的年轻人在他的年轻时即将陨落"
Brilliant young man cut off in the prime of his youth."
当然我问 "我们该怎么做？"
But of course I said,"What can we do?
"有什么我们可以做的"
What can we do to sort of
"需要做理疗么？"
Can we get physiotherapy?
"有没有什么能帮到忙吗？"
Can we get anything like that that will help in any way?"
他说 "事实上 没有
He said,"Well,actually,no.
"真的 我不能帮上一点忙 差不多 就是这样"
There's nothing I can do,really. More or less,that's it."
我21岁生日后不久
Shortly after my 21 st birthday...
我来到医院检查
I went into hospital for tests.
他们取了我的手臂肌肉样本
They took a muscle sample from my arm...
把电极插在我身上
stuck electrodes into me...
把显影剂注入我的脊椎
and injected some radiopaque fluid into my spine...
然后把床倾斜用X光扫描
and watched it going up and down with X-rays...
从头扫到尾
as they tilted the bed.
我被诊断为ALS
I was diagnosed as having ALS
肌萎缩性脊髓侧索硬化症
amyotrophic lateral sclerosis
又叫做运动神经元疾病
or motor neuron disease,as it is also known.
医生没有治疗方案
The doctors could offer no cure...
告诉我只剩下2年半的时间可活
and gave me 21/2 years to live.
我来到毕业生休息室
I went into the graduates' common room...
找有谁能一起吃饭的
looking,really,for someone to have lunch with.
没有人我期望的那样能够陪我一起吃午饭
There was nobody around that I particularly wished to have lunch with...
这时 史蒂芬进了房间
and then Stephen walked through the door.
我不知道他在牛津干什么 我已经忘记了
I don't know what he was doing at Oxford. I've certainly forgotten now.
史蒂芬慷慨地出去
And so Stephen generously went off...
买了些喝的
to buy the drinks...
带回来放在桌子上
and brought them and put them on the table.
他放下一品脱啤酒
And as he put his pint of beer down...
他分了一下
he spilled it.
我高兴地说
I sort of said genially...
"哦 老天 尽情喝吧"
"Oh,heavens. Drinking at this time of day!"
然后他告诉我 他在阿登布鲁克有三个星期了
He then told me he'd been in Addenbrooke's for three weeks...
他们做了一系列的检查
and they'd done a whole series of tests...
诊断出
and they'd decided...
他得了什么病
what was wrong with him.
他很平静的告诉我
And he told me very straight and flat...
他将渐渐地不能掌控
that he was gradually going to lose...
自己的身体
the use of his body...
到最后
that eventually...
只有心脏和肺
only his heart and his lungs...
大脑还能工作
would still be operating,and his brain...
他们告诉他
and that they'd told him that...
最终基本上全部瘫痪
eventually he would essentially have the body of a cabbage...
但是他仍然能够很好思考
but his mind would still be in perfect working order...
他将无法和别人交流
and he would be unable to communicate with the rest of the world.
那时候我很迷茫
My dreams at that time were rather disturbed.
在我被确诊之前
Before my condition had been diagnosed...
我对生活非常厌倦
I had been very bored with life.
好像没有什么可以值得做的
There had not seemed to be anything worth doing.
但是当我从医院出来的一瞬间
But shortly after I came out of hospital...
我想我快要完蛋了
I dreamt that I was going to be executed.
我突然意识到我还有很多值得做的事
I suddenly realized there were a lot of worthwhile things...
如果还有时间的话
I could do if I were reprieved.
我完全理解 他失去了信念
I knew perfectly well that he had no faith...
然后
and...
对我而言 那让我心里更加难受
to me,that made it the more difficult...
因为一般人遭遇这种悲剧都会问自己 "为什么偏偏是我？
because you must ask yourself,"Why me?
"偏偏是这种病？偏偏在我正值青春的时候？"
Why this? Why now?"
但他不同 他就那么完全坦然地接受了
But he just totally,flatly accepted...
接受了即将发生的事情
that this was what was going to happen to him.
据我推测 那时候他开始了一些工作
As far as I can gather,at that point he started to do some work.
一开始 我并不觉得我的研究
At first,there did not seem much point...
能有什么意义
in working at my research...
因为我根本没指望活到能够
because I didn't expect to live long enough...
完成我的博士学位
to finish my PhD.
然而 时间一天天过去
However,as time went by...
看上去 似乎病情进展延缓了
the disease seemed to slow down.
我开始能理解广义相对论
I began to understand general relativity...
还在工作中取得了一些进展
and made progress with my work.
不过 一直以来真正支撑着我的是
But what really made a difference was...
我那时已经与一位叫简·王尔德的姑娘订了婚
I had got engaged to a girl called Jane Wilde.
她是我生命的支柱
This gave me something to live for...
同时 这也意味着我得找份工作
but it' also meant I had to get a job...
如果我真心想和她结婚
if we were to get married.
史蒂芬那时已经确诊 简也清楚地知道
Stephen was already ill. Jane knew it.
这是史蒂芬又一个幸运之处
And it was another instance of Stephen's luck,you know
在对的时间遇见对的人
meeting the right person at the right time...
你想想 史蒂芬那时无比沮丧
because Stephen was very,very badly depressed...
并不怎么情愿继续他的工作
and he wasn't very much inclined to go on with his work.
他被告知生命只剩两年半的时间
He'd been told he's only got 2 and a half years.
在那种境况下你能做什么
What can you do in that time?
然而与简的相遇给他注入了勇气
But meeting Jane really put him on his mettle...
接下来 他又开始了工作
and he started to work.
我曾想探寻
I wanted to understand...
宇宙是如何起源的
how the universe began.
爱因斯坦的广义相对论
Einstein's theory of general relativity...
表明宇宙正在膨胀
showed that the universe was expanding.
但并没有一个答案来直接回答最关键的问题
But there was no answer to the crucial question...
"一定要有一个大爆炸"
"Must there have been a Big Bang...
"来开启时间的进程吗？"
a beginning to time?"
然后 当我在剑桥上三年级时
Then,in my third year at Cambridge...
罗杰·彭罗斯有了关于
Roger Penrose made his discovery...
恒星死亡的发现
about the death of stars.
我记得和一位朋友 艾弗·罗宾逊的讨论
I remember talking to this friend,Ivor Robinson...
那次讨论真是一场思想的碰撞
and we were having this animated conversation...
后来我们得过一条马路
and then we had to cross a road...
当然 我们过马路的时候 谈话中断了
and as we crossed the road,of course,the conversation stopped...
然后我们到了路的另一边
and then we got to the other side.
很碰巧的是 我在过马路的时候想出一个点子
Evidently,I had some idea crossing the road...
但接下来我们了捡起之前的话题 那个点子就从我脑子里不翼而飞了
but then the conversation started up,and it got completely blotted out of my mind.
直到晚些时候 在朋友回家之后
It was only later,after my friend had gone home...
我突然感到一阵奇妙的兴奋
and I began to have this strange feeling of elation
那感觉妙极了
feeling wonderful.
我不知道自己当时为何那样 于是我向前梳理这一天的思绪
I couldn't figure out why I should feel like that,so I went back over the day...
回想究竟是什么事情让我产生了这种感觉
thinking all possible things which might have contributed to such a feeling...
后来我慢慢挖掘出这个想法
and then gradually I unearthed this thought...
就是在大街上的那个
which I'd had while crossing the street.
当时彭罗斯告诉我这个结论
Penrose announced this result...
当恒星无限坍缩时
that when stars collapse indefinitely...
他们会变得奇异
they will become singular...
只需要满足一些很宽松的条件就会这样
as long as some very broad conditions are satisfied...
很多人都同意这一点
that everybody would have regarded as reasonable.
我记得史蒂芬·霍金当时快要三年级了
And I remember Stephen Hawking,who was then approaching...
他还是研究生 他说
his third year as a research student,saying...
"多有趣的结果"
"What very interesting results.
"我很好奇是否能应用它们"
I wonder whether they could be adapted...
"来理解宇宙的起源"
to understanding the origin of the universe."
他脑子里想的是 如果你像这样想像
And what he had in mind,you see,was that if,just mentally...
让时光倒流
you reverse the sense of time...
那么这个正在膨胀的宇宙就会变成一个坍缩中的系统
you can think of the expanding universe as a collapsing system.
这就像一个异常巨大的恒星正在坍缩
It's a bit like a very giant star collapsing.
罗杰·彭罗斯证明了
Roger Penrose proved...
一个垂死的恒星会在其自身重力的作用下坍缩
that a dying star,collapsing under its own gravity...
最后变成一个奇点
eventually shrinks to a singularity
一个拥有无穷大密度而没有体积的点
a point of infinite density and zero size.
我意识到 如果我颠倒时间进行的方向
I realized that if I reversed the direction of time...
那么这个坍缩的过程就变成膨胀
so that the collapse became an expansion...
于是我就能证明
I could prove that...
宇宙确实是有起源的
the universe had a beginning.
然而 我的证明
But my proof...
是建立在爱因斯坦广义相对论的基础上
based on Einstein's theory of general relativity...
这同时也表明我们无法理解
also showed that we cannot understand...
宇宙究竟是如何起源的
how the universe began...
因为它表明 所有的科学理论
because it showed that all scientific theories...
包括广义相对论本身
including general relativity itself...
都会在宇宙起源时分崩离析
break down at the beginning of the universe.
我们在纽约的空间物理研究院
We had this meeting...
召开了一次会议
at the Institute of Space Physics in New York.
我说 "在我们得到最终结果前"
I said,"Before we reach a final conclusion...
"我们得把另一样东西扔进"
we ought to throw into the pot...
"这个大熔炉"
still another object
"一个因重力而完全坍缩的物体"
a gravitationally completely collapsed object.
"哦 当你使用了这么一个说法"
Well,after you've used the phrase...
"一个因重力而完全坍缩的物体" 十遍之后
"a gravitationally completely collapsed object" ten times...
你会意识到最好给它起个名字
you conclude you've got to get a better name.
正是那时候我想到了这么一个词
So that's when I switched...
"黑洞"
to the word "black hole."
"黑洞" 这个约翰·惠勒灵光一闪想到的词 应运而生
The word "black hole," which John Wheeler coined,suddenly caught on.
从此以后 每个人都接受了它
Everybody adopted it,and from then on...
全世界所有的人 不论身处莫斯科
people around the world in Moscow...
美国
in America...
英国 还是什么地方
in England and elsewhere
都知道了他们一直以来谈论的都是同一个东西
could know they were speaking about the same thing.
情况远不止如此 突然之间
And not only that,but suddenly...
所有这些奇思妙想都传达给了公众
the whole range of concepts got through to the general public...
而且科幻小说家们一下子都能谈论
and even science-fiction writers all of a sudden...
有关黑洞的一切
could talk about it.
今晚 我的朋友们
Tonight,my friends...
我们一同站在宇宙探索中
we stand on the brink of a feat unparalleled...
一个无与伦比的胜利旁
in space exploration.
如果我的穿梭机所取回的数据
If the data on my returning probe ship...
与理论计算结果相符
matches my computerized calculations...
我就要亲身探索从未有人胆敢到达的地方
I will travel where no man has dared to go.
进入黑洞吗？
Into the black hole?
进入
In...
穿过
through...
一路向前
and beyond.
为什么 这太疯狂了
Why,that's crazy!
哈 这不可能
Ha! Impossible!
质量巨大的恒星收缩时
As a massive star contracts...
它的重力会变得如此之强
its gravity becomes so strong...
以至于连光都不再能逸出
that light can no longer escape.
依任何物质都无法逃离的边界划定一个范围
The region from which nothing can escape...
它的内部就是黑洞
is called a black hole...
而它的边界就是所谓的事件视界
and its boundary is called the event horizon.
你不妨这么看待事件视界
One might say of the event horizon...
像丹特所说 如同地狱的入口
what Dante said of the entrance to hell
"汝等进入此地 须弃绝一切所望"
"Abandon all hope,ye who enter here."
我曾被邀请
I was once asked to actually...
作为评审员
be an adjudicator...
来审核这样一篇论文
on an essay of which the subject was...
"如何进入一个黑洞并且生存下来"
"How to fall through a black hole and live."
审核它的困难在于 我不知道
Now,the problem I had was that I wouldn't know...
怎样才能把奖颁给它
how to give out the prize...
因为 如果我说 "这文章看起来不错"
because if I said,"That looks like a good essay"...
那么唯一能证实它的方法就是
the only real way of showing this was right...
如文章所说 真的去做这么一个实验 进入黑洞
was to actually follow it,to do the experiment and fall in.
可是 进入黑洞之后呢
But then,having fallen in
我觉得把这文章的作者一起带进黑洞是个好主意
I would assume taking the person who wrote the essay with you
问题在于 你俩要如何把结果告诉世界上的其他人？
the question would be,how do you tell the rest of the world?
要不要把颁给他们的奖带着
Do you take the prize in that you give to them...
而且他们进入到中心之后怎么办？
and what do they do with it when they get to the center?
相信我
Believe me...
我已等待多时 等一个你这样的人
I've been waiting a long time for someone like you...
来记录这个伟大的时刻
to record this moment.
谢谢你 博士
Thank you,Doctor.
我准备好了
Then I'm ready.
为人类最伟大的航行 我已经就绪
Ready to embark on man's greatest journey.
显然也是最冒险的
Certainly his riskiest.
风险是多么的微不足道
The risk is incidental compared to...
获得有关未知的伟大真理的可能就在眼前
the possibility to possess the great truth of the unknown.
就在那里
There...
自然的普适规则
long-cherished laws of nature...
将会被打破
simply do not apply.
它们灰飞烟灭
They vanish.
那生命呢？
And life?
生命？
Life?
生命永恒
Life forever.
如果你观察一名宇航员
If you were watching an astronaut...
莽撞地跳进一个黑洞
foolhardy enough to jump into a black hole...
这时候他手表上的时间是
at some time on his watch
比如说 12:00
say,12:00
他接下来穿过事件视界
he would cross the event horizon...
然后进入黑洞
and enter the black hole.
可是不论你等多久
But no matter how long you waited...
你都永远不会看到他的手表走到12点
you would never see the astronaut's watch reach 12:00.
理论上发生的是 手表上的每一秒
Instead,each second on the watch...
都会看起来越来越长
would appear to take longer and longer...
直到午夜前的最后一秒
until the last second before midnight...
它会持续到永远
would take forever.
因此 如果一个人要跳进黑洞
Thus,by jumping into a black hole...
他可以肯定 自己的形象会永远存在
one could ensure that one's image lasted forever.
但图像会迅速地消逝
But the picture would fade very rapidly...
并且变得模糊不清 谁都看不见
and grow so dim that no one could see it.
当一个人消失在黑洞中时
As somebody disappears into a black hole...
如果从外面观察 就会发现
as seen from the outside,it looks as though...
时间似乎变慢了 这个移动着的人
time actually slows down,and the person who's moving
至少他认为自己在移动
at least he's thinking he's moving...
他也许正在飞船中以正常的语速讲话
he's perhaps talking in his spaceship at a normal rate
但听起来是变慢了 最后在某一个特定的位置
seems to slow down and ends up being frozen...
被冻结起来
in a particular position...
从视界外观察就是如此
as seen by somebody watching him from the outside.
而且你永远不会看见他冻结之后发生的事情
And as seen from the outside,you never see what happens after that.
那个宇航员自己 则什么都不会注意到
The astronaut wouldn't notice anything special...
当他的手表到达午夜时
when his watch reached midnight. ..
他就穿过视界
And he crossed the event horizon...
进入黑洞
into the black hole...
直到他最终抵达奇点
until,of course,he approached the singularity...
被挤成肉泥
and was crushed into spaghetti.
人在穿越视界时
One can fall through this event horizon...
不会感觉到异样 甚至不知道自己穿越了视界
without feeling anything,without noticing it.
大约一周的坠落之后 人会觉得自己被什么东西捏着
After about a week of falling,one begins to feel the pinch...
变得越来越长
and one extends longer and longer...
而且稍稍变瘦
and gets slightly thinner.
接下来 当然 他开始被挤扁
And,of course,one begins to get squeezed...
直到他变得又细又长
until one gets very long and very thin...
让人看不下去
and rather nasty.
大概在第二个周末 他该已经落入了黑洞的中心 而且必死无疑
By the end of two weeks,one's fallen right into the center and is,of course,dead.
当外面的世界渐渐从你的视野中消失的时候
Before you lose sight of the outer world...
你能看到未来的事情发生 而且进行的越来越快
you would see things happening and see them at a greater rate...
看起来就像电影胶片
so that it would look like a firework display.
不过令人沮丧的是 尽管你能看见
The frustration would be that,although you would be able to see...
未来的事情一件件发生在你眼前 但是它们发生得太快
everything that happens in the future,it would be going so fast...
以至于 科学地来说 你根本没时间你分析它们
that from a scientific point of view,you'd have no time to analyze it.
甚至来不及看清楚
You wouldn't be able to take it in.
最后事情会进行得飞快
Eventually things would be going off so fast...
爆炸的力量也越来越强
and it would be so explosive that you yourself would be...
最终你被爆炸撕裂 然后一切都没有了
destroyed by the explosion,and that would be the end.
如果能以这么种方式结束自己的生命 想想还很激动呢
But it would be a very exciting way to end one's life.
说真的 如果有得选 我肯定会这样
It would be the way I would choose if I had the choice.
在宇宙的漫长历史中
In the long history of the universe...
许多恒星都用尽了核反应燃料
many stars must have burned up their nuclear fuel...
最后坍缩成一团
and collapsed in on themselves.
实际上黑洞的数量
The number of black holes may be greater...
也许要大于可见的恒星
than the number of visible stars...
一共约有1000亿个黑洞
which totals about a hundred thousand million...
这还只算了我们银河系而已
in our galaxy alone.
我们也得到一些证据
We also have evidence...
证据表明在我们的星系中心
that there is a very large black hole...
有一个无比巨大的黑洞
at the center of our own galaxy.
朋友们问我 "那个 如果黑洞是黑的"
Friends ask me,"Well,if a black hole is black...
"你要怎么看到它呢？"
how can you see it?"
于是我就说 "你总该去过舞会的吧？"
And I say,"Have you ever been to a ball?
"舞会上那些"
Have you ever watched the young men...
"穿着黑色燕尾服的年轻男子"
dressed in their black evening tuxedos...
"和着白色礼服的姑娘们"
and the girls in their white dresses...
"手拉着手转圈"
whirling around,held in each other's arms...
"当灯光暗下来后"
and the lights turned low...
"你就只能看到姑娘们了"
and all you can see is the girls?
"打个比方 如果一个女孩子是一颗普通的恒星"
Well,the girl is the ordinary star...
"而男子是一个黑洞"
and the boy is the black hole.
"尽管你不能看到男子 正如你无法看到黑洞"
You can't see the black hole any more than you can see the boy...
"但那个转着圈的姑娘能让你确信"
but the girl going around gives you convincing evidence...
"一定另有什么拉着她转圈"
there must be something there holding her in orbit."
有天晚上 我的女儿露西刚出生不久
One evening,shortly after the birth of my daughter,Lucy...
上床之前
I started to think about black holes...
我开始思考黑洞
as I was getting into bed.
我的身体缺陷让上床这一过程十分缓慢
My disability makes this rather a slow process...
所以我有的是时间
so I had plenty of time.
突然之间 我意识到
Suddenly I realized...
事件视界的面积
that the area of the event horizon...
必须随着时间的流逝而增大
must always increase with time.
视界面积的增大
The increase in the area of the event horizon...
很容易让人联想到一个叫做熵的物理量
was very reminiscent of a quantity called entropy...
它用来度量一个系统的混乱程度
which measures the degree of disorder of a system.
这其实是一种常识
It is a matter of common experience...
如果你把一些东西放任不管
that disorder tends to increase with time...
它们会倾向于变得无序
if things are left to themselves.
有天 雅各布·贝肯斯坦走进办公室
Jacob Bekenstein came into the office one day.
"雅各布啊" 我说
"Jacob," I said...
"有件事我总是想不清楚"
"lt always troubles me...
"当我把一杯热茶放在一杯凉茶边上时"
when I put a hot teacup next to a cold teacup.
"通过让热量从一个杯子转移到另一个上"
I've increased,by letting heat flow from one to the other...
"我增大了宇宙的混乱度"
the amount of disorder in the universe.
"但是 雅各布 如果一个黑洞恰好经过"
But Jacob,if a black hole swims by...
"这时候我把两杯茶都扔进去"
and I drop both teacups into this...
"我岂不是就隐藏了我让熵增大的证据 是吗？"
I've concealed the evidence of my crime,have I not?"
贝肯斯坦是个十分严谨的人
Bekenstein's a man of great integrity...
他当时看起来很疑惑 不过一会儿他就回来了
and he looked troubled,and he came back to me later...
"不 你没有" 他开口说
and he said,"No,you have not...
"这样并不能掩饰你之前的所作所为"
concealed the evidence of your crime.
黑洞会记录下你行为的痕迹"
The black hole records what's happened to you."
史蒂芬·霍金读了
Stephen Hawking read the paper...
贝肯斯坦在其中声明了这个结论的论文之后
in which Bekenstein announced this result...
觉得它太荒谬了
Thought it was preposterous...
他决定要证明它是错的
and decided to prove it was wrong.
我的发现让雅各布·贝肯斯坦做了如下假设
My discoveries led Jacob Bekenstein to suggest...
事件视界的面积
that the area of the event horizon...
实际上就是一个黑洞的熵
actually was the entropy of a black hole.
但是 这个假设有一个致命的缺陷
But there was one fatal flaw. ..
在贝肯斯坦看来
In Bekenstein's idea:
如果黑洞有熵
If black holes have an entropy...
那么它们就得有温度
they ought to have a temperature.
而如果黑洞有温度
And if they have a temperature...
那么他们就有辐射
they ought to give off radiation.
可是 既然任何东西都不能逃离黑洞
But how could they give off radiation...
为什么黑洞会有辐射呢？
if nothing can escape from a black hole ?
不过最后证明
As it turned out...
贝肯斯坦基本上是正确的
Bekenstein was basically correct...
但却是以一种让人惊异的方式
though in a manner far more surprising...
这方式超出任何人 包括他本人 的意料之外
than he or anyone else had expected.
当他的双手慢慢失去运动能力时
As he gradually lost the use of his hands...
他不得不开始
he had to start developing
精心挑选研究项目
carefully choosing research projects...
那些只需要在脑袋里进行几何运算
that could be tackled and solved...
就能处理好的项目
through geometrical arguments that he could do pictorially in his head.
此外 他还发展了一套非常强力的工具 其他任何人都不曾有过
And he developed a very powerful set of tools nobody else really had.
在某种程度上 当你失去一套工具时
So in some sense,when you lose one set of tools...
你能发展出另一套工具 不过新的工具
you may develop other tools,but the new tools...
能解决的难题是和之前那套工具不同的
are amenable to different kinds of problems than the old tools.
而如果世上掌握这套工具的人只有你一个
And if you're the only master in the world of these new tools...
那么有些问题只有你能解决 其他人都无能为力
that means certain kinds of problems you can solve and nobody else can.
直到1973年
My work up to 1973...
我的工作都在广义相对论的范畴内
was in general relativity...
它们被总结在一本我与乔治·埃利斯合著的书中
and was summarized in a book I wrote with George Ellis called...
大尺度下的时空结构
The Large Scale Structure of Space-Time.
那时候 书写对我而言已经很艰难了
Even then,it was difficult for me to write things down...
所以我更倾向于以图形和图表的形式
so I tended to think in pictures and diagrams...
在脑海中进行思考
that I could visualize in my head.
我记得那次探望史蒂芬和简的经历
I remember visiting Stephen and Jane...
他们那时还住在剑桥
at their home in Cambridge.
晚饭过后
After supper in the evening...
当史蒂芬要上床休息时
when it was time for Stephen to go to bed...
简坚持 而史蒂芬也默认 我猜这是通常的情况
Jane insisted and Stephen acquiesced I guess this was standard
史蒂芬自己尝试上楼梯
that Stephen make his way up
我已经记不清是一层还是两层楼梯
I've forgotten whether it was one flight of stairs or two alone...
这一时期 霍金已经不再能行走
and this was a period when he could no longer walk.
他是这么上楼的 他抓住楼梯栏杆的柱子
The way he got up the stairs was,he grabbed hold of the pillars...
把自己拉上去
that support the banister and pulled him up with the strength
用自己上肢的力量把自己拉起来
pulled himself up the stairs with the strength of his own arms...
一级一级地向上拉
dragging himself up...
从一楼到二楼
from the ground floor up to the second story...
好像花了一辈子的时间 缓慢而艰难
in a long,arduous effort.
简解释说
Jane explained that...
这是他物理疗法的一个重要部分
this was an important part of his physical therapy...
能够尽量保持他的协调能力
to maintain his coordination...
还有肌肉力量
and strength as long as possible.
刚开始的时候 我看得心痛不已
At first it was sort of heartrending...
看着他艰难地拉着自己一步步上楼
to watch what appeared to be the agony of pulling himself up the stairs...
后来我意识到 这就是生命的一部分
until I understood it's just part of life...
像那样拖着自己上楼梯
pulling himself up the stairs like that.
广义相对论被视为
General relativity is what is called...
一种经典理论
a classical theory.
它预言 每个粒子
It predicts a single definite path...
都只有唯一确定的路径
for each particle.
但根据量子力学
But according to quantum mechanics...
存在一种概念叫做概率或者说不确定性
there is an element of chance or uncertainty.
在时空中
A particle does not have...
一个粒子并不只有唯一的路径
just a single path through space and time.
相反 有这么一个不确定原理
Instead,there is an uncertainty principle...
它表明 一个粒子的准确位置
according to which both the exact position...
和准确速度永不可能同时知道
and velocity of a particle can never be known.
我开始研究
I began investigating...
黑洞附近的粒子上
the effect quantum mechanics might have...
的量子力学效应
on particles near a black hole.
我发现 粒子实际上
I found that particles could escape...
是可以逃离黑洞的
from a black hole...
因此 黑洞并不完全是黑的
that black holes are not completely black.
一开始连我自己都无法相信这一点
At first I didn't believe it.
但当我又做了一遍计算之后
But when I redid the calculations...
我发现量子力学的这种效果是无法摆脱的
I couldn't get the effect to go away.
我见了马丁·李斯一面 他兴奋得都在颤抖
I met Martin Rees,and he was shaking with excitement...
他说 "你听说了没？那个"
and he said,"Have you heard? Have you heard...
"史蒂芬刚刚发现的东西？"
what Stephen has discovered?
"所有一切都不同了 都颠覆了 "
Everything is different! Everything is changed!"
我对自己的发现仍抱有怀疑
I was still unsure of my discovery...
所以我只告诉了少数几个同事
so I only told a few colleagues...
不过消息传得飞快
but word soon spread.
罗杰·彭罗斯在我生日当天打来电话
Roger Penrose phoned up on my birthday.
他兴奋之极 跟我聊得根本停不下来
He was very excited and went on so long...
于是我的生日晚宴就被冷落了
that my birthday dinner got quite cold.
真遗憾 晚宴上有鹅肉诶
It was a great pity,because it was goose...
我超喜欢的
which I'm very fond of.
对我而言 那简直就是个奇迹 因为计算过程复杂又混乱
To me it's a miracle,'cause it's a complicated and messy calculation.
当今这个时代我们再做这事儿就会顺手得多
We can now do these things very much better...
而且发生的事情看起来更加明晰
and it's more transparent what happens.
从这些混乱的计算中 他得出的结论是
But out of this messy calculation,he showed that black holes...
黑洞在量子力学效应下 并不是黑的
aren't black with this quantum mechanical effect.
宇宙中存在一种背景辐射
There was a residual radiation.
史蒂芬参加一次会议
Stephen came to a meeting...
人群一阵骚动
and people were flabbergasted.
我记得有人说 "史蒂芬你肯定错了"
I remember someone saying,"You must be wrong,Stephen.
"你的理论我一句话都不信"
I don't believe a word of it."
我曾经说过
I once said that I was unhappy...
对粒子负能量子的产生的解释让我很不满意
with the explanation given in terms of negative energy particles being created.
不过 我觉得这是科学思辩的一部分
But I feel this is part of the controversy of science.
你必须有所取舍 我很开心自己参与了这场思辩
You must have the give and take,and I'm delighted to be a part of that.
这是个很有趣的过程
That's what makes it fun.
当人们的脑子里萦绕着闹人的疑惑时
If you all sat down and said,"Oh,lovely"...
如果所有人都试图忽略他们
when you do have niggling questions in your mind...
那么这实际上对科学毫无意义的
that's not doing a service to science.
不过我对这并不抵触
But I was not antagonistic to it in any way...
除非脑子里不安生的人是我
except for that one time when I questioned.
最终我说服自己
I finally convinced myself...
黑洞确实有辐射
that black holes radiate...
我找到一种黑洞辐射的机制
when I found a mechanism through which this could happen.
根据量子力学
According to quantum mechanics...
空间充满虚粒子
space is filled with virtual particles...
和反粒子
and antiparticles...
它们成对地以实物形式存在
that are constantly materializing in pairs...
分离然后靠近
separating,coming together again...
共同湮灭
and annihilating each other.
在黑洞附近
In the presence of a black hole...
上述一对虚粒子中的一个
one member of a pair of virtual particles...
可能落进黑洞
may fall into the hole...
这样剩下在外面的一个就失去了伙伴
leaving the other member without a partner...
没法湮灭
with which to annihilate.
于是就成为辐射
The forsaken particle appears to be radiation...
被黑洞释放出来
emitted by the black hole.
所以黑洞并不能永远存在
And so black holes are not eternal.
它们以一个不断增加的速率蒸发
They evaporate away at an increasing rate...
直到在一次巨大的爆炸中灰飞烟灭
until they vanish in a gigantic explosion.
量子力学允许粒子和辐射
Quantum mechanics has allowed particles and radiation...
从黑洞这种终极监狱中
to escape from the ultimate prison
逃逸出去
a black hole.
爱因斯坦从未接受过量子力学
Einstein never accepted quantum mechanics...
正是因为它特有的概率与不确定性
because of its element of chance and uncertainty.
他说 "上帝是不玩骰子的"
He said,"God does not play dice."
看来爱因斯坦可能错了
It seems that Einstein was doubly wrong.
黑洞中的量子效应
The quantum effects of black holes...
表明上帝不仅玩骰子
suggest that not only does God play dice...
他有时还把骰子扔到
he sometimes throws them...
无法观测的地方
where they cannot be seen.
他说他自己
He says himself...
嗯
that,uh...
要是没有生病 就不会取得如今的成就
he wouldn't have got to where he is if he hadn't been ill.
而且我觉得这确实有可能
And I think that's quite possible...
因为就像塞缪尔·约翰逊所说
because it's like Johnson said:
如果你就要上绞刑架
The knowledge you're to be hanged in the morning...
精神便会最集中
concentrates the mind wonderfully.
从某种程度上来说 他专注于科研
And he has concentrated on this in a way...
我觉得他本不会对科学有太大兴趣 因为他对生活中的很多事情
I don't think he would have,because he took a great interest...
都有极大的兴趣
in a lot of things in life...
而且我不知道他会不会同样专注于科研
and I don't know that he'd have applied himself the same way...
如果他能够像以前健康的时候一样 所以在一定程度上
if he'd been able to get around as he used to do,so in a way...
是的 即便如此 我也不认为有人能得那样的病是幸运的
No,I can't think anyone's lucky having an illness like that,even so.
但是相对于其他人来说 他的不幸要更少
But it's less bad luck for him than it would be for some people...
因为他能用他的头脑好好地活着
because he can so much live in his head.
当我住到霍金的家里时 我通常
When I lived with the Hawking family,I would usually get up...
七点十五或者七点半起床 洗个澡
around 7:15 or 7:30 and take a shower...
然后读一点圣经并且做祈祷
and then read in my Bible some in the morning and pray...
八点十五的时候下去叫史蒂芬起床
and then go down at 8:15 to get Stephen up.
吃早饭的时候我经常告诉他我在圣经上读的东西
And at breakfast I would often tell him what I'd been reading in the Bible...
希望这些东西最终能有所影响
hoping that this would eventually have some influence.
然后我们就开始工作
So then we would go into work...
通常我们会看看是否有
and usually we'd go in and see if there were any scientific papers...
其他人发表的科研论文
that people sent out.
我确实发现尽管霍金才华横溢 但是他阅读得相当慢
I did discover that despite Hawking's great brilliance,he does read quite slowly.
我阅读速度是他的两倍
I could read about twice as fast as he.
当然他必须要边读边记
But of course he would have to read to remember it...
因为对于他来说回过头来再看是非常困难的
because it would be very difficult for him to go back and access the thing...
而我能相当快速地略读这些论文
whereas I could skim the paper rather quickly and see...
并看看 "这里头没有什么有趣的东西？"
"Is there something interesting in this?"
要是我想研究它 我就能找出来接着看
If I wanted to work on it,I could pick the thing up and look at it.
黑洞辐射
Black hole radiation...
向我们展示了引力坍缩
has shown us that gravitational collapse...
并不像我们曾经想象的那样
is not as final as we once thought.
如果一个宇航员掉进了黑洞
If an astronaut falls into a black hole...
他将会以辐射的形式
he will be returned to the rest of the universe...
回到宇宙中
in the form of radiation.
因此 在某种意义上
Thus,in a sense...
这个宇航员再生了
the astronaut will be recycled.
然而这是一种可怜的永生形式
However,it would be a poor sort of immortality...
因为当他被撕碎的时候
because any personal concept of time...
个体的时间概念就会走到尽头
would come to an end as he is torn apart...
只存在于在黑洞之中
inside the black hole.
世间万物
All that would survive...
都有他的质量或能量
would be his mass,or energy.
有一年 霍金一家人带我一起
One year,the Hawkings took me along...
那时韦·文茨来到
when We Wenz' to a cottage in Wales...
威尔士惠河畔的小屋
near the River Wye...
这个小屋在半山腰上
and this cottage was up a hill...
那有一条
and there was a bit of...
通往小屋的铺砌的小道
a paved little sidewalk that went up to the cottage...
当然 我并没有上去
which I had not been up,and of course...
我想尽可能少走几个来回
I wanted to do it in the least number of trips I could imagine...
所以我们把史蒂芬的电池放到椅子下面
so we put Stephen's batteries under his chair...
他的椅子有空间放电池 还能把额外的电池放那下面
his wheelchair has space for batteries ... and put extra batteries under there...
史蒂芬没意识到我把电池放下面了
which Stephen didn't realize that I'd put under there...
所以他没意识到他的轮椅负载那么重
so he didn't realize his wheelchair was as heavily laden.
史蒂芬走到我前头一点 然后准备转弯
Stephen got quite a bit ahead of me,and he was turning the corner...
走向他的屋子 但那是在一个斜坡上
to go around to his house,but that was on a slope...
所以我向上看 注意到史蒂芬的轮椅在慢慢地向后滑
so I looked up,and I noticed Stephen's wheelchair slowly tipping backward.
当然 我大概在十米外
Of course,I was about ten meters away...
我开始冲向他 但是在他跌入灌木丛之前
and tried to run up there,but I was not able to get there...
我没能赶上
rapidly enough before he toppled backward into the bushes.
所以那是一幅有点可怕的景象
So it was a bit of a shocking sight...
看着这个精通万有引力的大师正在克服
to see this master of gravity getting overcome...
地球那微弱的重力
by the weak gravitational force of Earth.
对于我来说 最糟糕的事情之一就是总有人到这里来
One of the worst things for me would be having people there all the time.
不能一个人安静地待会 我没法忍受
Never alone. I couldn't bear that.
然而他发现这些事很有趣
And yet he finds things funny...
而且他享受这生活 冲向所有地方
and he enjoys life and he goes dashing about all over the place...
我觉得这是一种巨大的勇气
and I think this is tremendous.
一种我所没有的勇气
But it's a sort of courage I haven't got...
他父亲也没有 我们都没有 我们只能表示敬佩
and his father hadn't got it,and we cannot but admire it...
只能怀疑他究竟如何获得这份勇气 真的
but wonder how on earth he got it,really.
那一定有五十人
There must have been 50 people there...
我站在一个角落
and I was standing off in a corner...
安静地看着
sort of watching quietly...
看了几分钟 正在放松
for a few minutes,relaxing...
史蒂芬就在那 离我不远
and Stephen was over there,not far from me.
简走向史蒂芬看着他
Jane walked over to Stephen and looked at him.
他正坐在那 头放在大腿上
He was sitting there with his head in his lap...
好像只有史蒂芬能把他的头放在大腿上
like only Stephen can put his head in his lap.
简对史蒂芬说
And Jane said to Stephen...
"你看起来很痛苦 史蒂芬 坐直了"
" You look miserable,Stephen. Sit up straight.
"你的一些客人不理解"
Some of your guests don't understand...
"你正在思考物理 享受着美好的时光"
that you're thinking about physics and having a wonderful time.
"这让你看起来身处痛苦之中 坐直了和你的客人聊聊天"
It looks like you're in pain. Sit up and go talk to your guests."
1979年
In 1979...
我被选为卢卡斯数学教授
I was elected Lucasian Professor of Mathematics.
这可是牛顿当年做过的职位
This is the same chair once held by Isaac Newton.
他们有一本巨大的书
They he ve a big book which e very university teaching officer...
每一位大学教授都应在上面签字
is supposed to sign.
在我成为卢卡斯教授一年后
After I had been Lucasian Professor for about a year...
他们意识到我没签过
they realized I had never signed.
所以他们把书带到我办公室
So they brought the book to my office...
我签得非常困难
and I signed with some difficulty.
那是我最后一次签我名
That was the last time I signed my name.
我对宇宙起源和命运的兴趣
My interest in the origin and fate of the universe...
在我参加一个梵蒂冈的宇宙学会议的时候
was reawakened when I attended...
被重新唤醒
a conference on cosmology in the Vatican.
在那之后
Aftewards,we were granted...
我们被罗马教皇接见
an audience with the pope.
他告诉我们
He told us that it was all right...
研究大爆炸之后的宇宙演化
to study the evolution of the universe...
这挺好
after the Big Bang...
但是我们不应该研究大爆炸它本身
but we should not inquire into the Big Bang itself...
因为那是创造的一瞬间
because that was the moment of creation...
那是上帝的工作
and therefore the work of God.
我很高兴他不知道
I was glad that he did not know...
我刚给出的主题是
the subject of the talk I had just given...
宇宙没有起点的可能性
the possibility that the universe had no beginning...
没有开天辟地的那一瞬间
no moment of creation.
70年代早期有一些理论 第一种类型的创造论
There were theories in the early '70s ... the first type of creation theories...
他们从一个固定的外部时空出发
where the people concerned started off with a fixed,external space and time...
这个外部时空永远都是空的
which for eternity was empty...
然后 突然 因为某种未知的原因
and then suddenly,for some unknown reason,the universe nucleates...
宇宙到某个特定的点成核 砰 它爆炸了
at a particular point and then,bang,it blows apart.
但问题是当时间和空间出现在经典理论中
But the trouble is that when space and time appear in the classical theory...
那个点本身是个数学上的奇点
that actual point itself is a singular point in the mathematics.
数学无法处理了 所以…
Mathematics breaks down,and so...
你不能用这个来得出创造论
you cannot use that to give you a creation theory.
如果一个人回到从前
If one goes back in time...
回到大爆炸的奇点
one comes to the Big Bang singularity...
那里的物理法则就不复存在
where the laws of physics break down.
但是有另一个时间线的方向
But there's another direction of time...
可以顺着那个方向来避免奇点
that one can go in which avoids the singularity.
这被称作时间的虚方向
This is called the imaginary direction of time.
在虚时间里
In imaginary time...
不需要
there need not be any singularities...
形成任何时间上有开始或结束的奇点
which form a beginning or end to time.
当你进入虚时间 你就有这种相当特殊的可能性
When you come to imaginary time,you have this rather peculiar possibility...
拥有"现在"
of having a "now," as it were...
它不需要
without necessarily having a sort of a chain...
建立在过去的基础上
of past moments.
如果我从我们所处的瞬间开始 跑向过去的时光
If we start where we are at the moment and start running backwards in time...
那么在很长的一段时间里 事物都会非常正常的运作
then for a long time,things work perfectly normally.
但是当你往前越走越远时
But as you begin to get further and further back towards...
当你愈发远离传统的实时间图像时
what would be the origin point in the conventional real-time picture...
你就能发现时间的性质改变了
you'd find that the nature of time changes...
虚的一部分越来越显著
that the imaginary component becomes more and more prominent...
直到进入经典理论的奇点
until what ought to have been the singular point in the classical theory...
才变得光滑 然后你就看到这个美丽的碗的画面
gets smoothed away,and you have this beautiful picture...
宇宙诞生的碗
of these bowls where the creation of the universe is pictures...
我们现在在这 光滑的碗是过去
of where we are now,and a smooth bowl of the past...
那里没有奇点 只是光滑的形状
where there's no initial point,just a sort of smooth shape.
只要宇宙有一个起点
So long as the universe had a beginning...
我们就应该有一个创造者
We could suppose it had a creator.
但是如果宇宙是完全独立的
But if the universe is completely self-contained...
无限并且无界
having no boundary or edge...
它就不会被创造或者毁灭
it would neither be created nor destroyed.
它很简单地存在着
It would simply be.
那么 把创世者摆在什么位置？
What place,then,for a creator?
你所能说的是创世者存在于宇宙之中
All you can really say is that the universe is...
因为它是一个独立的数学结构
because it's a self-consistent mathematical structure.
它没有过去的 因为它不像一个点被创造出来这样的设想
There's no past because,unlike the creation-as-a-point scenario...
对于宇宙来说 没有什么被创造
there's nothing for it to be created in.
所以说 创造于虚无之中的说法有点欠妥
So to say it's created from nothing is a bit of a misnomer.
"虚无"这个词的用法会令人误解
It's a misleading use of the word "nothing."
宇宙表现出的并不是空间的虚无
it's not just that there was empty space in which the universe appeared,
你可能把这称之为"虚无"
which you might call "nothing."
宇宙里确实什么都没有 因为连创造都没有
There was really nothing at all,because there wasn't even a creation event.
动词过去式的用法在这些理论里不太合适
The use of a past tense in a verb becomes inappropriate in these theories.
不幸的是 当人们支持实时间 时态就被创造了
Unfortunately,tenses were set up when people believed in real time,of course...
至今我们都没有一种语言形式来描述虚时间的时态
and we don't yet have a linguistic form to describe tenses in imaginary time.
"时间"这个词 可不是作为
The word "time" was not handed down from heaven...
礼物从天堂那流传下来的
as a gift from on high.
时间的概念
The idea of time is a word...
只是个被人类发明的词
invented by man...
如果它让人产生疑惑
and if it has puzzlements connected with it...
这是谁的错？我们的错
whose fault is it? It's our fault.
过去与未来
Where does the difference...
有着什么不同？
between the past and the future come from?
科学法则
The laws of science do not distinguish...
没法区分过去与未来
between the past and the future.
但在日常生活中
Yet there is a big difference...
过去与未来有着巨大的差别
between the past and future in ordinary life.
你能看到茶杯
You may see a cup of tea fall off a table...
从桌子上跌到地上 摔成碎片
and break into pieces on the floor...
但你从没见过杯子能自己合好
but you will never see the cup gather itself back together...
然后跳回桌子上
and jump back on the table.
混乱或者熵的增加
The increase of disorder,or entropy...
可以区分过去和未来
is what distinguishes the past from the future...
给出时间的方向
giving a direction to time.
他在瑞士生病了
He fell ill in Switzerland.
他回来的时候戴着呼吸机
When he came back,he was on a ventilator.
因为他戴着呼吸机 要把管子插到喉咙里
Because he's on a ventilator,you've got a tube down your throat...
所以就不能说话了
and therefore you can't speak,just for that reason.
那段时期 可能是两个月
For that period,which may have been a couple of months...
我每两天或每三天会在医院里呆一夜
I spent probably one in two nights,one in three nights,at the hospital...
因为他在医院里
because when he was in hospital...
没法和护士交流
he couldn't communicate with the nurses.
虽然不像是什么大病
It's not just like being seriously ill...
但是护士不能理解史蒂芬的需求
but you're in a position where the nurses couldn't understand what Stephen wanted.
如果史蒂芬不舒服 他们不知道是为什么
If Stephen was uncomfortable,they couldn't tell why.
在我得肺炎之前
Before I caught pneumonia...
我说话越来越含糊不清
my speech had been getting more slurred...
所以很少有人能很清楚地理解我
so that only a few people who knew me Well...
了解我
could understand me.
但是至少我能够交流
But at least I could communicate.
我以向秘书口述的方式
I wrote scientific papers...
来写论文
by dictating to a secretary...
并且通过翻译参加研讨会
and I gave seminars through an interpreter.
后来 一个气管改造手术
And then,a tracheostomy operation...
让我完全失去了说话的能力
removed my ability to speak altogether.
之后的很长一段时间 好吧 看起来是很长时间
After a long time ... well,it seemed like a long time...
有人想出这个绝妙的小发明
somebody came up with this brilliant gadget.
剑桥医院里没有这东西
They didn't have it at the Cambridge hospital.
他们从伦敦的什么地方拿到了
They got it from somewhere in London.
这是个高科技 你不用出声就可以与人交流
This was high technology ... how you can communicate with a person with no voice.
它是有机玻璃的 大概这么大
It's a plastic piece of Perspex about so big...
你能看到字母像这样排列着 中间有个洞
and you've got the letters of the alphabet arranged like that,and a hole in the middle.
朝着别人举着它
You hold it up between you and the other person.
他们看一个字母时 你能知道他们看的是哪个字母
They look at a letter,and you can see which letter they're looking at ...
绝大多数都行 有时也不能确定
most of the time. Sometimes you can't be sure.
所以你要有耐心来拼出想要说的话
So you would get the patient to spell out what they wanted.
每一个字母 你必须看着挑选出A
So each letter ... they have to look to pick out the A.
你说 "A？" 你明白了吗？就像个猜字游戏
You say,"A?" Did you get it right? It's like a guessing game.
史蒂芬不愿意接受他不能说话了
Stephen wasn't willing to accept that he wasn't going to speak again...
他想他会做出让步
and he thought he would be giving in...
如果找到一种比说话更好的交流方式
by trying to find a method of communicating other than speech.
我记得有个晚上我过去
I remember I went in one evening...
这是第一次他想
and this was the first time that he asked...
起床用电脑
to be gotten out of bed to use the computer.
有时他们会让他坐着 因为他不能总是躺着
Sometimes they'd sit him up so he wasn't lying in bed all the time...
就像你对待一个病人一样 但是这次当我出现的时候
as you do with a patient,but this time when I turned up...
他问护士 能不能让他起床
he asked the nurse,could he be gotten out of bed...
那样他可以用电脑 而且他做到了
so he could use the computer,and he did.
打完招呼之后 我记得他打在电脑上第一句话是
I remember the first thing he typed on there after saying hello...
史蒂芬总是那么地礼貌
Stephen's always very polite about things like that...
"你愿意帮助我完成我的书吗？"
was,"Will you help me finish my book?"
加州的一位电脑专家
A computer expert in California...
听说了我的近况
heard of my plight...
发给我一个电脑程序
and sent me a computer program...
叫做均衡器
called Equalizer.
它可以让我从屏幕上的一系列的选项中
This allowed me to select words...
选择单词
from a series of menus on a screen...
通过按我手中开关
by pressing a switch in my hand.
这些单词再发给一个
These words could then be sent to a speech synthesizer...
装在轮椅上的语音合成器
attached to my wheelchair.
令我惊喜的是
Much to my surprise...
我发现我能够
I found I was able to communicate...
比以前更好地进行交流了
much better than before.
当最后他从医院回到家
When eventually he went home from hospital...
他被告知他需要二十四小时监护 每一个人都说
he was told he needed 24-hour nursing,and everyone was saying...
"他要怎么继续工作？"
"How is he going to go in and do work?
"工作时也要有护士陪着吗？"
Is he going to trail around with nurses after him in the office?"
当然是那样
And of course he did.
他们最初讨论让他在家工作
They talked originally of him working at home...
他对此并不满意
which he wasn't happy with.
所以 在家恢复了一段时间之后
And so,after a period of recuperation at home...
他就决定回到他的办公室
he just decided to go back into the office.
而他从家到办公室的途中
And he'd make the trip from his house to the office...
我不太清楚 用轮椅走了半英里
which is,I don't know,half a mile in his wheelchair...
有一个护士跟着他
with a nurse walking along with him.
那时他依然到处转转
This is at the time when he was still driving around...
带着一个袋子和鼻滴
with the bag and the nasal drip...
工作 回家
going into the department,working,going back home.
我开始想象
I began to wonder what would happen...
当宇宙停止膨胀
when the universe stopped expanding...
开始收缩之后 会发生什么
and began to contract.
我们会看到破碎的杯子
Would we see broken cups...
自己合好
gather themselves together off the floor...
从地上跳回桌上？
and jump back onto the table?
我们会记得明天的物价
Would we be able to remember tomorrow's prices...
在股票市场大赚一笔？
and make a fortune off the stock market?
对于我来说
It seemed to me...
宇宙一定会回到一个平滑有序的状态
the universe had to return to a smooth and ordered state...
当它再次坍缩的时候
when it recollapsed.
时间就开始倒退
If this were so,time would go backwards...
当宇宙开始坍缩的时候
when the universe began to collapse.
在收缩阶段人们会倒着活
People in the contracting phase would live their lives backward.
他们会死在出生之前
They would die before they were born...
当宇宙缩小 能再获青春
and get younger as the universe got small again.
最终回到子宫
Eventually,they would return to the womb.
头一次 他给我留了一个问题
He gave me my first problem to do.
他让我看看这个数学问题
He asked me to look at this mathematical problem.
通常当他给出一个问题 他的脑海里
Usually when he gives a problem,he has a good idea...
会有答案的大概样子
of what the answer should be.
我看了一下 花了我几个月
I went to look at it,and it took me a few months...
来理解这是什么东西 然后回来说 "我知道答案了"
to understand what it was about,and I came back and said,"I get this answer."
他对我说 "不 这不是我所期望的"
And he said to me,"No,that is not what I expected."
我说 "这就是我得到的" 所以我走向黑板 解释它是什么
I said,"That's what I get." So I went to the blackboard,explained what it was.
他说 "考虑特殊情况了吗？" 我说 "没考虑"
He said,"Did you think about that particular case?" I said,"No,I didn't."
所以我又回去了
So I went back...
然后计算他告诉我的东西
and I calculated what he'd talked to me about.
在我回去的一个星期后 我说 "史蒂芬 我得不到这些东西"
I came back a few weeks after,and I said,"Stephen,I don't get this thing.
"我仍然得出了一开始的答案"
I still get the same answer I had originally."
所以他对我说 "不不不"
So he said to me,"No,no,no,no.
"这没用 你想过那些东西吗？"
This doesn't work. Did you think about that?"
我说 "哦 不 我忘了考虑特殊情况"
I said,"Oh,no. I'd forgotten about that particular case."
所以我回去重新开始计算
So I went back to the drawing board and started calculating again...
再一次 我得到了相同的答案
and again I got the same answer.
所以我又回来见史蒂芬 这拖延了两三个月
So I went back to see Stephen,and this dragged on for two or three months.
最后他对我说
Finally he said to me...
"可能你的某一个近似是无效的"
"Maybe one of your approximations is not valid."
所以我和我的同事决定用计算机做这件事
So me and a colleague decided to do the thing with computers.
这花了大把时间来写程序
This takes a lot of time to Write the programs...
还要确定程序是正确的
and to be sure the program was correct.
我们得到答案 仍然和我之前说的一样
We get the answer,and it was still the way I'd said before...
而不是史蒂芬说的那种 所以我们去见史蒂芬 说 "看到了吗？还是这样"
and not the way Stephen said,so we went to see Stephen and said,"See? Again."
我犯了一个错误
I had made a mistake.
我使用的宇宙模型太过简单
I had been using too simple a model of the universe.
当宇宙开始收缩时
Time will not reverse direction...
时间不会反转
when the universe begins to contract.
人们还会继续变老
People will continue to get older...
所以等着宇宙再次坍缩 回到我们的青春
so it is no good waiting until the universe recollapses...
这不现实
to return to our youth.
爱因斯坦曾经问了一个问题
Einstein once asked the question...
"在构建宇宙的时候"
"How much choice did God have...
"上帝有多少种选择？"
in constructing the universe?"
如果我的宇宙没有边界的假设是对的
If my proposal that the universe has no boundary is correct...
那么上帝在创世上
he had no freedom at all...
毫无选择的余地
to choose how the universe began.
他唯一可以选择的是
He would only have had the freedom...
宇宙所服从的法则
to choose the laws the universe obeyed.
然而 这可能
This,however,may not have been...
也没有太多选择
all that much of a choice.
可能只有一种统一理论
There may well be only one unified theory...
这种理论允许各种复杂结构的存在
that allows for the existence of structures...
像人类一样复杂
As complicated as human beings...
人类能研究宇宙法则
who can investigate the laws of the universe...
能够探究上帝的本质
and ask about the nature of God.
我不知道这些实验有多明确
I don't know how clear-cut these experiments are...
但是有过关于意识时间的实验
but there are experiments that have been done on the timing of consciousness...
它们似乎都会得到一幅非常奇怪的图景
and they seem to lead to a very odd picture...
而这图像也没有什么确切的意义
which doesn't even quite make consistent sense.
我不确定这些实验的精细
Whether refinement of these experiments...
是否能摆脱这种异常
might get rid of this kind of anomaly I'm not sure...
但是它看起来有点像与意识有关的奇怪的东西
but it does look a little as though there is something very odd about consciousness...
还像是未来在某种程度上影响了过去
and somehow almost as though the future affects the past in some way...
这种影响只在非常小且有限的尺度上
over a very tiny,limited scale,but something maybe of the order...
或者是什么只在一秒内有序的东西
of a reasonable fraction of a second.
没理由相信
And there's no reason to believe...
一个人的意识体验
that one's conscious experience...
在另一些阶段不会成为
shouldn't be part of somebody else's...
别人意识的一部分
at some other stage.
我不知道这是否可信 说一个人死后
I don't know if it's fair to say what happens after one dies...
他可能会成为另一个人
but it's a plausible picture...
但这貌似是很有可能的
that you could be somebody else...
并且某人可能是活在过去的某个人 而不是未来的
and that somebody else could be somebody that lived in the past,not in the future.
即使只有一种可能的大统一理论
Even if there is only one possible unified theory...
即一套准则和方程
that is just a set of rules and equations...
那是什么扰乱了这些等式
what is it that breathes fire into the equations...
制造出一个它们所描绘的宇宙呢？
and makes a universe for them to describe ?
为什么宇宙要自寻烦恼？
Why does the universe go to all the bother of existing?
是否是大统一理论如此势不可挡
Is the unified theory so compelling...
以至于引起其自身存在的问题？
that it brings about its own existence?
或许 他需要一个创造者？
Or does it need a creator?
如果是这样
And,if so...
是谁创造了创造者？
who created him?
我想我会说宇宙有个目的
I think I would say that the universe has a purpose.
它不是偶然地莫名其妙地存在
It's not somehow just there by chance.
我想它是
I think it's ... Yeah.
那么的
So...
它是
it's... it's...
我想有些人会持这么一种观点 宇宙就在那
Some people,I think,take the view that the universe is just there...
它只是不停地运行
and it sort of runs and runs,and it just sort of computes...
我们偶然发现了我们身处其中
and we happen somehow by accident to find ourselves in this thing.
但我觉得这不是一种
But I don't think that's a very fruitful...
正确的看待宇宙的方式
or helpful way of looking at the universe.
我认为宇宙有更深层次的东西
I think that there is something much deeper about it.
在实时间中 就是我们所生活的这种时间
In real time,the time in which we live...
宇宙有两种可能的命运
the universe has two possible destinies:
它可能永远继续扩张
It may continue to expand forever...
或者 它可能在大收缩中
or it may recollapse and come to an end...
再次坍缩 最终结束
at the Big Crunch.
这与大爆炸相当类似
It would be rather like the Big Bang...
但过程相反
but in reverse.
现在我相信宇宙最终会在
I now believe that the universe will come to an end...
大收缩中结束
at the Big Crunch.
然而 我确实
I do,however,have certain advantages...
比其他厄运先知更占优势
over many other prophets of doom.
无论一百亿年之后会发生什么
Whatever happens ten billion years from now...
我都不希望被证明是错误的
I don't expect to be around to be proved wrong.
我所知道的所有画面
Of all the pictures that I know...
任何最简单的宇宙学的结论
the simplest of any cosmology...
就是宇宙是封闭的
is that in which the universe is closed...
拥有有限的寿命
has a finite lifetime...
会坍缩
and collapses with the same kind of collapse...
像黑洞坍缩那样
that a black hole does.
如果结果确实是那样
If it should turn out that indeed...
宇宙的生命是有限的
the universe is limited in its life...
那么它的生命
how is that different from the life...
与我们每个人的又有什么不同？
of each one of us?
在3月5日 星期二的晚上
On the evening of Tuesday,March 5fh...
大概10:45
at about 10:45. . .
我正准备回去皮恩斯的公寓
I was returning to my flat in Pinehurst.
天色很暗 又下着雨
It was dark and raining.
我来到格兰芝路
I came up to Grange Road...
看见车灯正在接近
and saw headlights approaching...
但是我判断他们离我足够远
but judged that they were far enough away...
使我能安全地通过
that I could cross safely.
那辆车一定是开得非常快
The vehicle must have been traveling very fast...
因为当我仅仅到路中间时
for when I got just past the middle of the road...
我的护士就惊呼 "小心 "
my nurse screamed,"Look out!"
我听到轮胎在滑行
I heard tires skidding...
一阵强风从我轮椅后面吹来
and my wheelchair was struck a tremendous blow in the back.
我最后躺在路上
I ended up in the road...
腿搭着剩下的轮椅
with my legs over the remains of the wheelchair.
这场事故弄坏了我的轮椅
The accident destroyed my wheelchair...
还毁了
and damaged my computer system...
我用来交流的计算机
with which I communicate.
我要在头上缝十三针
I required 13 stitches in my head...
但是几天之后我就能够回去工作了
but I was able to go back to work several days later.
我对那一段的记忆
The memories I have are very much...
大概是
kind of...
史蒂芬当时的样子
visual pictures of what Stephen was...
以及他在那种情形下的情况
of seeing Stephen in certain situations.
他总是在动
He was always moving.
总是
Always.
呃 几乎没安静过
Well,hardly ever still.
关于他的表情和姿态也一样
It was the same thing about his face and gesture...
他曾常用的那些 我应该说
which he used a great deal,I should say...
但这仅仅是记忆了
but it's only memory.
最近我找到一些照片
I found some photographs recently...
使我想起每一个人的样子
which reminded me of the general look of everybody...
我必须说史蒂芬非常像他现在的样子
and I must say Stephen looked very much like he does now...
如果你能想起以前的他
if one thinks of him like that.
他非常强烈地相信
He does believe very intensely...
人类的思想有无限可能
in the almost infinite possibility of the human mind.
在你知道你不能之前
You have to find out what you can't know...
你一定能发现那些你没法知道的事情 不是吗？
before you know you can't,don't you?
所以我认为思想一点都不应该被束缚
So I don't think that thought should be restricted at all.
为什么你不该继续想那些无法想象的东西？
Why shouldn't you go on thinking about the unthinkable?
或许有些人已经开始了
Somebody's got to start sometime.
想想在一个世纪以前有多少事情是无法想象的
Think how many things were unthinkable a century ago...
还有人们曾想过的
and yet people have thought them.
它们经常看起来不切实际
And often they also seemed quite unpractical.
史蒂芬说的东西
Not all the things Stephen says probably...
并不一定都被当作真理
are to be taken as gospel truth.
他是一个探索者 他正在探索
He's a searcher. He's looking for things.
有时他可能是胡说八道 好吧 难道我们不也是吗？
And sometimes he probably talks nonsense. Well,don't we all?
但关键是
But the point is...
人类必须思考
people must think.
必须继续思考
People must go on thinking.
他们必须试着扩展知识的边界
They must try to extend the boundaries of knowledge...
有时他们甚至不知道从何开始
and they don't sometimes even know where to start.
你不知道边界在哪 不是吗？
You don't know where the boundaries are,do you?
你不知道你的起点是什么
You don't know what your taking-off point is.
如果我们确实发现了一个完整的宇宙理论
If we do discover a complete theory of the universe...
它应该及时就成为广泛的原则
it should in time be understandable...
被每个人所理解
in broad principle by everyone...
而不仅仅是少数的科学家
not just a few scientists.
然后我们所有人
Then we shall all...
无论哲学家 科学家 还是普通人
philosophers,scientists,and just ordinary people...
都能够参与讨论
be able to take part in the discussion of why it is...
我们和这宇宙为什么存在
that we and the universe exist.
如果我们找到答案
If we find the answer to that...
这将是人类理性的
it would be the ultimate triumph...
最终胜利
of human reason...
因为我们知道了
for then we would know...
上帝的想法
the mind of God.